Register of the Charles Burton Burdick papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Charles Burton Burdick papers
1917-1987
67037
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
The Charles B. Burdick collection includes writings and research materials relating to Austrian mobilization and alleged espionage in World War I; Germany and expatriated Germans in World War II; and Ralph H. Lutz, director of the Hoover Institution.
Burdick, Charles Burton, 1927-.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1967.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1927 May 12 Born in San Jose, California, USA
1940-1944 Attended Lincoln High School in San Jose, CA
1945 June 5- 1946 November 23 Served in the United States Military during World War II
1946-1949 Attended San Jose State University (SJSU). Graduated with a B.A. from History
1954 Obtained Ph.D from Stanford University
1957 Joined SJSU History Department
1976 Became History Department Chair at SJSU
1988 Retired from SJSU faculty
1998 June 6 Died in Los Gatos, CA
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection includes writings and research materials relating to the American academic and historian Charles B. Burdick. Included are a manuscript on Austrian mobilization in 1914, immigration and military records concerning alleged Austrian espionage in World War I, and a biography of Ralph H. Lutz, director of the Hoover Institution. Also included is research concerning the S.S. Marine Jumper for an article Burdick wrote entitled "The Expulsion of Germans from Japan, 1947-1948."
Arrangement Statement
The collection is organized into 3 series: Writings; Visser family file; and S.S. Marine Jumper file
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace.; Lutz, Ralph Haswell, 1886-1968.; Espionage, Austrian--United States.; Secret service--Austria.; World War, 1914-1918--Austria.; World War, 1914-1918--Secret service.; World War, 1914-1918--United States.
- Writings, 1935-1987
  - Written by others, 1935
    - The Mobilization of the European Powers in the Summer of 1914: Austria-Hungary, 1935 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Written by Burdick, 1974-1987
    - Quiet Footsteps: Ralph H. Lutz and the Hoover Institution, 1974 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - "Tradition and Murder in the Wehrmacht", 1987 (Box-folder 1: 3)
- Visser family file, 1915-1966
  - Summary, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Immigration records, 1915-1920
    - 1915-1916 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - 1917 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - 1918-1920 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Photostat copies, 1915-1920 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Notes from Military Intelligence, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - "A House on Navidad Street", 1966 (Box-folder 1: 10)
- S.S. Marine Jumper file, 1947
  - Jumper Journal, 1947 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Miscellany, 1947 (Box-folder 1: 12)